Holocaust Collection 0008.003.004a
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Holocaust
1937-2008
0008.003.004a
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
12.0 Linear feet Paper format: 7 document boxes and 1 box of photographs
The Holocaust collection consists of personal testimonies, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and photographs. Most of the material focuses on the experiences of survivors and witnesses who settled in the Greater Hartford area. Some material is related to national and international Holocaust studies and commemorations. The most significant portion of the collection consists of audio and videotaped interviews of local Holocaust survivors.
Related Archival Materials note
Many of these interviews are also available in transcript form. See list below or People chart for details. Steven Spielberg, as part of his Survivors of Shoah project, interviewed other local survivors. Those oral histories can be accessed at: http://www.vhf.org/. As of this date, July 6, 2006, last names of interviewees are not given in the online version, but are available on the CD version.
Adler, Martin; Avigdor, Isaac, Rabbi, Poland; Baer, Inge; Binford, Mira Reym; Chameides, Leon, Doctor; Chase, David T.; Eichenwald, Jeanette; Engel, Chiam; Faust, Trudy; Fiss, Harry; Frankfurter, George; Fritz, Renee Schwalb, Consultant; Frydman, Jack; Gaster, Berthold, Journalist/The Ledger, b.1926, Vienna; Goldsher, Issac; Gutman, Nathan; Hershfield, Lotte; Hirth, Ann; Homar, Abraham; Israel, Beatrice Theisebach; Jacobs, Fred; Jacobs, Regina; Kadden (Katten); Karliner, Walter; Kirchheimer, Julius; Klemens (Clemens), Ruth; Kopman, Helen, Warsaw, Poland; Korduner, Saul; Korzenick, Joseph; Kubran, Jack; Kubran, Lea; Lazowski, Phillip; Lazowski, Ruth; Leifer, Mania, Krylow, Poland; Levy, Henry, b. 1926, Salonica, Greece; Libitsky, Eva; Libitsky, Martin; Lubka, Sam; Luftglas, Roman; Melcher, Helene; Meriden, David; Merin, David, Poland; Merin, Leonard, Poland; Nachtigal, Samuel; Neuhaus, Rose; Ostfeld, Bernard; Patron, Rachel, Writer, Poet; Post, Florence, Homemaker, b. 3/4/1936, Kovna, Lithuania; Ressler, Molly; Rothenberg, Lottie; Rubel, Lore; Scheer, Bernard, Author, Dental Technician, b. 1926, Podhajce, Poland; Schwartz, Bernard; Schwartz, Lori; Shainfarber, George; Sheiman, Ilse; Shenkman, Herbert; Silberman, Leo L., Physician; Silverton, Leo; Sluis, Henry, Real Estate Investor, Musician, Antwerp, Belguim; Soumerai, Eve; Springer, Irene; Sprung, Ita, Poland; Sprung, Leon; Stargardter, Hans; Strauss, Herbert; Strauss, Lotte; Tec, Nechama, Author and Educator, Doctor; Vogel, Jack; Wallerstein, Jules; Weilheimer, Richard; Weis, Magda; Wynberg, Selma; Catholic Church; Connecticut, USA; Denial; Education; Film & Performing Arts; Genocide; Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Nazis/ Nazi Germany; Survivors; War Criminals; Witnesses
- Series I: General
  - General/Art and music/Karas, Joza, research on music composed in Terezin, 1979-1992; Newspaper clippings, music program (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Mr. Karas is a Holocaust survivor who is known for his written work, "Music in Terezin 1941-1945". A violinist and instructor of music at the Hartt School, Mr. Karas was born in Poland, raised in Chechoslovakia.
    In addition to newspaper articles discussing Mr. Karas' biography and community works, this folder includes a musical program to the Hartford Symphony Orchestra presenting "Brundibar".
    Karas, Joza, Music Instructor, Poland; Holocaust; Music; Nazi concentration camps
  - General/Bingham, Hiram, 2004-2006; Newspaper clippings (Ledger) (Box 1)
    Newspaper articles featuring biographical information and events related to Mr. Hiram Bingham.
    Bingham IV, Hiram "Harry", Attorney, Salem, CT; Businesses & Professions -- Attorney; Holocaust; World War II
  - General/Catholic Church, 1998-2001; Newspaper clippings (Ledger & Courant) (Box 1)
    Newspaper articles from the late 1990's relating Jewish responses to Catholic Church and John Paul II position on Shoah.
    Catholic Church; Holocaust
  - General/ Commemorations, 1984; Magazine programs (Box 1)
    File contains commemoration program held by the U.S. Holocaust Memorial Council, April 1984, and a booklet on the Holocaust Memorial Museum, its first five years (1993-1998).
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust
  - General/Connecticut, 1993-1998; Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    Holocaust related newspaper articles published by CT Jewish Ledger.
    Bridgeport, CT; Holocaust; Krystallnacht
  - General/Contemporary Accounts/Articles & Manuscripts, 1932-1943; 0.01 Linear feet 1943 Telegraphed Bulletin (1943) original, several orignial newspaper clippings, New Republic booklet, and photocopies of newspaper articles (Box 1)
    This file contains several newspaper articles related to anti-Nazi protests during the early 1940s, and other community happenings in and around Hartford during the early WWII period. Contents include an original telegraph bulletin related to the liquidation of the Vilna Ghetto (1943) and a booklet from the New Republic entitled, "The Jews of Europe": How to Help Them", (1943).
    Cohen, Emma Perlstein, b.December 1, 1904, Hartford, CT; Gordon, Yale; Prinz, Joachim; Silverman, Morris, Rabbi; Wise, Jonah B.; Wise, Stephen S., Rabbi; Anti-Semitism; Holocaust; pre-Nazi Germany
  - General/ Demonstrations & Protests, 1933-1985; Newspaper clippings, pamphlets, booklets, photocopies (Box 1)
    File contains several newspaper articles dating back to 1933 reporting Holocaust resistance and protest. Also, of special significance is a 1933 booklet entitled, "The Boycott is Our Only Weapon Against Nazi Germany", authored by Samuel Untermyer, and a 1946 booklet entitled "Balance Sheet of Extermination", authored by Jacob Lestchinsky.
    Anti-Defamation League; Anti-Semitism; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Nazi concentration camps
  - General/Denial, 1988-1997; Newspaper clippings, newsletters (Box 1)
    This folder contains several newspaper articles and editorials covering the topic of Holocaust denial or repudiation. Many of the articles published by the Jewish Ledger and the Hartford Courant.
    Anti-Defamation League; Denial
  - General/Denmark, 1997; Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    Folder contains two newspaper articles from the Jewish Ledger, dated 1997, that report about the "Little Boat That Could" -- a sea vessel named the "Gerda III" that rescued Danish Jews to nearby Sweeden in 1943. The article discusses how the ship ferried over 7200 Jews to saftey during the war and was visiting Mystic Seaport in 1998.
    Denmark; Holocaust survivors
  - General/Film and Performing Arts, 1983-2000; Newspaper clippings, programs (Box 1)
    This file contains many assorted newspaper articles reporting on performances, movies, television programs, etc. related to the Holocaust. Articles date back to 1983, but many are undated. There also are programs from the Yale Repertory Theatre from teh 2005 season - "Comedy on the Bridge" and "Brundibar". Additionally, the file contains a program from the JCC sponsored performance of "...I never saw another butterfly", with accompanying children's poetry from survivors of the Terezin Concentration camp.
    Breslau, Sharon; Arts & Entertainment; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Nazi concentration camps
  - General/Frank, Anne, 1983-1998; Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    The newspaper articles in this file discuss the ongoing legacy of Anne Frank as it has related to Hartford in the recent past.
    Frank, Anne; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors
  - General/Genocide, other occurances, 1993; Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    Single newspaper article relating Holocaust experience to ethnic cleasing in Bosnia.
    Life in Europe
  - General/Hitler, 1983; Newspaper clipping (Box 1)
    Editorial piece on Adolf Hitler, remembering Hitler's rise to power 50 years prior.Also article authored by Kahn from Jewish Monthly entitled, "A Long Night Settles On a Unsuspecting World".
    Kahn, Lothar, College Professor, Doctor; Holocaust; Nazis/ Nazi Germany
  - General/Hitler's Black Record: The Documented Story of Nazi Atrocities Against the Jews issued by the American Jewish Congress, 1943 March 1, one paper bound booklet; Very good condition, front cover right dog-earred tear, slight discoloration (Box 1)
    File contains an original copy of Hitler's Black Record: The Documented Story of Nazi Atrocities Against the Jews issued by the American Jewish Congress, 1943 March 1. (23pgs.)
    Anti-Semitism; Holocaust; Nazis/ Nazi Germany
  - General/Literature and Fiction, 1994/1999; Newspaper clippings; Gould, June, Author; Nolan, Han, Author (Box 1)
    Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Poetry
  - General/Maps of Nazi aggression, 1945, Original newspaper clipping and photocopies (Box 1)
    Original 1945 newspaper clipping of map, with caption 'How Nazis Struck for World Domination", from the Hartford Times.
    Maps; Nazis/ Nazi Germany; World War II
  - General/Mengele, Joseph investigation, 1980s, 1985; Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    New York Times news articles pertaining to testimony related to atrocities of Josef Mengele.
    Nazi concentration camps; Nazis/ Nazi Germany
  - General/Miscellaneous, 1994-2003; Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    Various newspaper articles discussing Holocaust matters in the 1990s.
    Brett, Audrey; Anti-Semitism; Holocaust; Nazi concentration camps
  - General/Nazi War Criminals, 1993/1997; Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    Two newspaper articles from the Jewish Ledger discussing community reations to war criminal news.
    Bodenheimer, Hans, Rabbi, Germany; Chase, David T.; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Nazi concentration camps; Nazis/ Nazi Germany; War Criminals
  - General/Published manuscripts, 1975-1978; Photocopied manuscripts (Box 1)
    File contains three photocopied manuscripts: Bauer, Yehuda (1978) "Against Mystification: The Holocaust as a Historical Phenomenon", Seattle: University of Washington Press. Noakes, J. and Pridham, G. eds. (1975) "Documents on Nazism 1919-1945". New York: Viking Press. Leopold, John A. (undated) "Nazi Determination and the Destruction of Dutch Jewry". Publication in the Holocaust Studies Annual.
    Anti-Semitism; Holocaust; Jewish life in Europe; Nazis/ Nazi Germany
  - General/Reparations and Compensation, 1990s; Newspaper clippings and program booklets (Box 1)
    This folder contains a series of newspaper articles concerned with the issue of Holocaust reparations for survivors. In addition, there is a booklet published by the Conference on Jewish Material Claims Against Germany and a published lecture by Saul Touster (1999) entitled "The Treatment of Jewish Survivors of the Holocaust, 1945-1948: Dilemmas of Law, Care, and Bureaucracy", delivered at Brandeis University.
    Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors
  - General/Research Papers, undated; Bound manuscript; Shatzer, Julie A. (Box 1)
    Shatzer, Julie A. "Exploring the Experience of Grandchildren Hearing and Retelling their Grandparents Holocaust Experiences". Smith College School of Social Work, 1996
    Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors; Research papers
  - General/Righteous Gentiles, 1994-2004; Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    This folder contains newspaper articles honoring Gentiles who acted heroically during WWII and beyond, aiding Jews persecuted during the Holocaust.
  - General/S.S. St. Louis, 1971; pamphlet, booklet (Box 1)
    1971 pamphlet reprinted from the American Jewish Historical Quarterly entitled, The St. Louis Tragedy. Also included is U.S Holocaust Memorial Museum publication on the "Voyage of the St. Louis".
    Holocaust survivors; S.S. St. Louis; World War II
  - General/Tzichor, Memory Books, The Tzebinia Kehilla, 1969; Bound book/ photo album (Box 1)
    This file contains a memorial testimony, told in text and pictures, of the Jewish people of Trzebinia, Poland who endured the sufferings of the Holocaust during WWII.
    Eastern European Jews; Holocaust
  - General/ "Vanished World: A Tribute to Roman Vishniac", undated (Box 1)
    This file contains a written script and other writings associated with "A Vanished World: A Tribute to Roman Vishniac". Flyer advertising the event is also included.
    Soumerai, Eve; Vishniac, Roman, August 19, 1897 --January 22, 1990; Ararat Lodge; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Nazi concentration camps; Nazis/ Nazi Germany; Shtetl life
  - General/Wallenberg, Raoul, 1997; Newspaper clipping (Box 1)
    Newspaper article reporting the stamp commemoration of Swedish diplomat who saved over 100,000 Jews during WWII by issuing Swedish passports.
    Wallenberg, Raoul, 08/04/1912, Sweeden; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors
  - General/Yanuck, Michael, "Waxing Philosophical", 2009; Photocopy of recollective essay; Yanuck, Michael, Author (Box 1)
    Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors; Memoir
- Series II: Survivors
  - Survivors/International/Hacker, Bronia, cousin of Bernard L. Bloom, 1995; Transcription photocopy; Hacker, Bronia, b. 01/16/1925, Lvov, Poland (Box 2)
    This document contains a translation of an interview conducted in French on the behalf of the Shoah Project with Bronia Hacker, who is the sole survivor of a once large Jewish family who lived in Poland before WW II.
    Questions posed by the interviewer are not included in the translation.
    In the course of WW II Bronia lost both her parents, her only sibling, and all her aunts, uncles, and cousins. At the end of the war she was completely alone and found herself in Vienna. Since she is a survivor of the Holocaust, she tells a story that includes a good deal of luck as well as tragedy.
    Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Life in Europe
  - Survivors/National/Miscellaneous, 1979-2000; Newspaper clippings and photocopies (Box 2)
    Various newspaper articles discussing the lives and contributions of Holocaust survivors dating back to 1979.
    Radin, Ruth Yaffe, Author, Hartford, CT; Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/National/Reunions, 1990; photocopy of Times Herald article (Box 2)
    Shainfarber, George; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/National/Second Generation, 1977; New York Times magazine [original] (Box 2)
    NY magazine article entitled "Heirs of the Holocaust; The Lingering Legacy for Children of Survivors". p. 12-14.
    Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/National/Spielberg oral history project, 1994; newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    1994 article from the Jewish Ledger promoting the need for the stories of Holocaust survivors to be documented by the Spielberg project.
    Holocaust survivors; Spielberg Project -- Shoah Visual History Foundation
  - Survivors/National/Virginia, 1983; Published booklet, poster, magazine article; Yom Hashoah. United Jewsih Federation of Tidewater, Virginia. (Box 2)
    File contains 1983 supplement to the UJF Virginia News, entitled "Yom Hashoah" sharing stories of Holocaust survivors. Also, included is Nandor Lazar's poster for Holocaust remembrance and an article describing his mission.
    Lazar, Nandor; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/National/Wisconsin, 1983; Bound paperback book (Box 2)
    This file contains a "Guide to Winconsin Survivors of the Holocaust", published in 1983 by the State Historical Society of Wisconsin in Madison. Contents include information about interviewees, maps, lists, and information regarding related collections.
    Holocaust; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/National/Yale oral history project, 1979-2000; Correspondence, manuscripts, newspaper articles, informative data; Garber, Dr. Meyer Delott, Principal of Burr Junior High School in Hartford, 11/14/1908-12/15/1991 (Box 2)
    File contains various letters and other forms of correspondence related to the development of the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies at Yale University. Some of the correspondence relates to involvement in this project by the Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford. On particular significance are listings of Holocaust survivors in the state of CT by city and local address, dated 1986.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    This file contains information concerning Holocaust survivors in Connecticut of a confidential nature. More specifically, names and addresses of CT survivors are catalogued by city location.
    Yale University.; Holocaust survivors; Jewish Federation of Greater Hartford; Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford; Yale University
  - Survivors/Connecticut/General, 1980-1998; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Various newspaper articles from the Jewish Ledger and other Hartford papers related to Holocaust recollections and activities of survivors.
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Adler, Martin, 1994; Newspaper clipping; Adler, Martin (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger newspaper editorial written by Martin Adler, a Holocaust survivor and member of the Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh.
    Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Avigdor, Isaac, 1983-2003; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Series of newspaper articles (1983-2003) about Rabbi Issac Avigdor.
    Avigdor, Isaac, Rabbi, Poland; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Baer, Inge, 1988; Newspaper clpipping (Box 2)
    Article relating Inge Baer's recollections of her Holocaust experience.
    Baer, Inge; Holocaust survivors; Krystallnacht
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Binford, Mira Reym, 1995; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant newspaper article featuring state resident Holocaust survivors, 1995.
    Binford, Mira Reym; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Chameides, Leon, 1989; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Chameides, Leon, Doctor; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Chase, David T. and Tec, Nechama, 1997; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    1997 Jewish Ledger article concerning a book entitled "The Triumphant Spirit", in which David Chase and Nechama Tec are featured along with the stories of other Holocaust survivors.
    Chase, David T.; Tec, Nechama, Author and Educator, Doctor; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Child survivors and hidden children, 1992-2002; newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    File contains a number of Ledger and other newspaper articles related to reunions and stories of children of the Holocaust in Connecticut.
    Children; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Clemens, Ruth (Klemens), 1984; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Newspaper article discussing Ms. Clemen's invovlement as a speaker at the Rabbi Leon Wind Religious School of Temple Beth Sholom in Manchester, CT.
    Klemens (Clemens), Ruth; Beth Sholom; Holocaust survivors; Manchester, CT
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Davis, Albert, 1995; Photocopy of newspaper clipping; Gaster, Adele Diane (Box 2)
    Davis, Albert; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Displaced persons, 2000; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant newspaper article featuring story about displaced persons after the Holocaust.
    Primus, Romana Strolchlitz; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Jewish Life in Germany
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Eichenwald, Jeanette, undated; photocopy (Box 2)
    Folder contains a biography of the professional and volunteer capacities of Jeanette Eichenwald.
    Eichenwald, Jeanette; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Engel, Chaim and Wynberg, Selma, 1990; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    West Hartford News articles dicussing presentations given by Holocaust survivors and camp escapees, Selma and Chaim Engel.
    Engel, Chiam; Engel, David; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Faust, Trudy, 1995; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (9/1/1995) featuring the story of Trudy Faust and her return to her home town for a reunion of Austrian Jews.
    Faust, Trudy; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Fiss, Harry, 2009; Photocopies and newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Biographical information and newspaper articles featuring Holocaust survivor Harry Fiss. Mr Fiss was employed as a clinical psychologist at the University of Connecticut Health Center in Farmington, CT and participated in the Nuremberg Trials as a translator.
    Fiss, Harry; Holocaust survivors; Nuremburg Trials
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Frankfurter, George, 1985; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (4/10/1985) featuring Holocaust survivor George Frankfurter's recounting of how Raoul Wallenberg had saved his life.
    Frankfurter, George; Wallenberg, Raoul, 08/04/1912, Sweeden; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Fritz, Renee Schwalb, 1991; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (05/19/1991) featuring the survivor story of Renee Schwalb Fritz of Bloomfield, CT.
    Fritz, Renee Schwalb, Consultant; Bloomfield, CT; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Frydman, Jack, 1988; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (04/21/1988) featuring a story onthe planned retirement of Holocaust survivor Jack Frydman from Mount Sinai Hospital.
    Frydman, Jack; Holocaust survivors; Mount Sinai Hospital
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Goldsher, Issac, 1930s-1940s; Original documents and photos (Box 2)
    Folder contains a series of photographs, documents, and newpaper articles related to the life of Issac Goldshur, much of which pertains to the liberation of the Bergen-Belson concentration camp. Included also are original marriage certificates from the Bergen-Belson British Occupation Zone and many photos of family members pre-dating and post-dating WWII.
    Goldsher, Issac; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Gutman, Nathan, 1985; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (04/27/1985) entitled "A Holocaust Survivor Sends a Message to the President".
    Gutman, Nathan; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Hershfield, Lotte, 1995; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Hartford Courant article (04/18/1995) featuring the story of Holocaust survivor Lotte Hershfield.
    Hershfield, Lotte; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Hirth, Ann, 1995; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Folder contains a Journal Inquirer newspaper article (4/20/1995) featuring a story about Ann Hirth and her parents experience of escaping Nazi Germany before the inception of WWII.
    Hirth, Ann; Agriculture & Farming; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors; Zionism
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Homar, Abraham, undated; Photocopy (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article featuring Abraham Homar's account his POW experience and of Gestapo plans to execute POW's during WWII.
    Homar, Abraham; Holocaust survivors; Jewish War Veterans
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Israel, Beatrice Theisebach, 1997; Newspaper clipping (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article featuring story of West Hartford, CT Holocaust survivor Beatrice Israel and her participation in a memorial commemoration in Linden, Germany.
    Israel, Beatrice Theisebach; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Jacobs, Fred and Regina, 1998; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Jewish Ledger article (02/06/1998) featuring the community work of Fred and Regina Jacobs. The Jacobs were both survivors of Auschwitz and later established their dry-cleaning business, Dan-Dee Cleaners in West Hartford, CT.
    Jacobs, Fred; Jacobs, Regina; Holocaust survivors
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Kadden (Katten) family, article by granddaughter Shira Springer, 2003; Newspaper magazine (Box 2)
    This folder contains a Boston Globe magazine (07/13/2003) with cover feature story on the Katten (Kadden) Family and their escape from Nazi Germany.
    Kadden (Katten); Holocaust survivors; Nazis/ Nazi Germany